Jonathan Krause Rare Newspaper and Magazine Collection 1648-1881 E302.1 .J76 E302.1 .J76
Lilly Library
- Colonial American and Early Republic Topics
  - Revolutionary War
    - RECOGNITION OF U.S. AND FRANCE BY SPAIN, Providence Gazette, August 22, 1778 (Item 628)
      See: Thomas Paine 480
    - GENERAL CLINTON'S MANIFESTO AND PROCLAMATION, The Town and Country Magazine, December 1778; Size: Small (Item 1051)
      The final attempt to keep American British, rejected by Adams and the Congress; too little, too late.
      Also BRITISH ABANDON BOSTON AND BLOCKADE OF QUEBEC
    - MANIFESTO OF CONGRESS (WRITTEN BY SAMUEL ADAMS OR GOUVERNEUR MORRIS) AS A MORALE-BOOSTING NATIONAL STATEMENT OF STRENGTH AND CONFIDENCE, DECLARING THE AMERICAN CAUSE JUST AND SUCCESS ASSURED, London Evening Post, December 19, 1778 (Item 1073)
      Response to Clinton's Manifesto. See Item 1051
    - RESOLUTION PASSED BY CONGRESS URGING PEOPLE TO RETALIATION (against British barbarism), London Evening Post, December 19, 1778 (Item 1074)
    - BATTLE OF CAMDEN, London Chronicle, October 7, 1780 - October 10, 1780; Size: Small (Item 629)
    - BATTLE OF YORKTOWN, Gentleman's Magazine, November 1781; Size: Small (Item 630)
    - KING GEORGE SPEECH CALLING AMERICA FREE AND INDEPENDENT, European Magazine and London Review, December 1782; Size: Small (Item 631)
    - KING GEORGE SPEECH CALLING AMERICA FREE AND INDEPENDENT, Gentleman's Magazine, January 1783; Size: Small (Item 632)
    - PRELIMINARY ARTICLES OF PEACE ENDING REVOLUTIONARY WAR, Pennsylvania Journal and Weekly Advertiser, March 15, 1783 (Item 633)
      Follows very closely the Definitive Treaty of Paris, September, 1783.
    - BILL RESTORING COMMERCIAL RELATIONS BETWEEN BRITAIN AND U.S. FOLLOWING REVOLUTIONARY WAR, Pennsylvania Packet, June 24, 1783 (Item 634)
  - Declaration of Independence
    - DECLARATION OF INDEPENDENCE, Gentleman's Magazine, August 1776; Size: Small (Item 635)
      First English printing.
  - Constitution
    - SYSTEM FOR THE FUTURE GOV'T OF THE U.S. HAVING BEEN AGREED SPECULATION ON CONTENT OF CONSTITUTIONAL CONVENTION, Massachusetts Gazette, August 24, 28, 1787 (Item 636)
    - VERY RARE LEAK FROM CONSTITUTIONAL CONVENTION AND ONE OF FIRST REFERENCES TO A FUTURE GOVERNMENT, Salem Mercury, September 4, 1787 (Item 637)
      See: Patrick Henry 229
    - U.S. CONSTITUTION, Gentleman's Magazine, November, December, 1787; Size: Small (Item 638)
  - Constitutional State Ratifying Conventions
    - MASSACHUSETTS CONVENTION, Connecticut Courant and the Weekly Intelligencer, January 28, March 31, 1788 (Item 639)
    - MASSACHUSETTS CONVENTION, New Hampshire Gazette, February 13, 1788 (Item 640)
    - NEW YORK CONVENTION, Connecticut Courant, July 14, 1788 (Item 641)
  - Bill of Rights and Amendments to the Constitution
    - PHILADELPHIA REPUBLICANS AGAINST CONSTITUTION AND PENNSYLVANIA FEDERALISTS FOR IT AND REMARKS ON AMENDMENTS, American Museum Magazine, April, June, 1789; Size: Small (Item 642)
      See: Benjamin Franklin 119 (April) and John Adams 3 (June)
    - VIRGINIAN (Jeffersonian and Anti-Federalist) PERSPECTIVE ON AMENDMENTS TO THE CONSTITUTION, Gazette of the United States, January 2, 1790 (Item 644)
    - FURTHER PROPOSED AMENDMENTS TO BILL OF RIGHTS, Gazette of the United States, March 13, 1790 (Item 645)
  - Whiskey Rebellion
    - PROCLAMATION OF MARYLAND COMMANDER AND PENNSYLVANIA GOVERNOR, American Daily Advertiser, August 23, 1794 (Item 671)
      See: Alexander Hamilton 195
    - REPORTS ON REBELLION, The Herald A Gazette for the Country, September 18, 1794 (Item 672)
  - Shays' Rebellion
    - SPEECH BY MASSACHUSETTS GOVERNOR STRONG AND REPORTS, Connecticut Journal, October 11, 1786 (Item 673)
    - REPORTS AND MISCELLANY, Massachusetts Gazette, July 17, 24, October 19, 1787 (Item 674)
      See: John Adams 1 (July 17, 24, October 19)
    - PETITION BY DANIEL SHAYS, Massachusetts Centinel, March 15, 1788 (Item 675)
- 19th Century American Individuals
  - Pre-Civil War Period
    - James Buchanan
      - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, New York Herald, December 28, 1859 (Item 752)
        One of the most racist speeches in history.
    - Henry Clay
      - REFUTING CHARGES MADE BY ANDREW JACKSON, National Journal, January 3, 1828 (Item 753)
      - IN DEFENSE OF THE AMERICAN SYSTEM, New York Spectator, March 6, 1832 (Item 754)
        One of the most famous speeches on economics in American history.
      - LETTER ON SLAVERY, EMANCIPATION, COLONIZATION, Examiner, March 10, 1849 (Item 755)
      - SPEECH ON MISSOURI COMPROMISE, Lynchburg Virginian, August 5, 8, 12, 1850 (Item 756)
    - Stephen Douglas
      - SPEECH ON POPULAR SOVEREIGNTY AND KANSAS NEBRASKA ACT, Boston Daily Times, February 2, 1854 (Item 760)
      - ARTICLE ON DIVISION BETWEEN FEDERAL AND LOCAL AUTHORITY(POPULAR SOVEREIGNITY IN THE TERRITORIES) AND CATALYST FOR LINCOLN'S CINCINNATI SPEECH IN 1859, Harper's New Monthly Magazine, September 1859; Size: Small (Item 761)
    - Andrew Jackson
      - LETTERS FROM THE BATTLE OF NEW ORLEANS, Aurora, February 14, 1815 (Item 779)
        See: War of 1812 746
      - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE AND INDIAN REMOVAL, Niles' Weekly Register, December 11, 1830; Size: Small (Item 780)
      - NULLIFICATION PROCLAMATION, Niles Weekly Register, December 15, 1832; Size: Small (Item 781)
      - MESSAGE TO CONGRESS ON NULLIFICATION CRISIS, The Evening Post, January 19, 1833 (Item 782)
      - MESSAGE TO CONGRESS ON NULLIFICATION CRISIS, Columbian Register, January 26, 1833 (Item 783)
    - Mordecai Manuel Noah
      - NOAH BEFORE MARYLAND LEGISLATURE DURING HEARINGS ON JEW BILL OFFERING LETTERS WRITTEN BY ADAMS, MADISON AND JEFFERSON TO HIM AS EVIDENCE TO LIFT RESTRICTIONS ON JEWS, Niles' Weekly Register, February 20, 1819; Size: Small (Item 841)
        Letter appearing only in Noah's book and presidential correspondence.
        See: John Adams 30 (pages 9-13)
      - CEREMONY CONSECRATING THE FOUNDATION STONE OF THE NEW HEBREW CITY OF ARARAT, Columbian Centinel, September 24, 1825 (Item 842)
      - ARARAT AND GRAND ISLAND SCHEME TO INGATHER JEWS FROM EUROPE AND ELSEWHERE IN AMERICA TO ESTABLISH NEW ZION, Niles Weekly Register, October 1, 1825, November 26, 1831; Size: Small (Item 843)
    - Dred Scott
      - DRED SCOTT DECISION, New York Observer, March 12, 1857 (Item 858)
      - DRED SCOTT DECISION, The State of Maine, March 17, 1857 (Item 859)
      - DISSENTING OPINION ON SCOTT CASE BY JUSTICE TURNER, National Era, April 2, 1857 (Item 860)
    - Nat Turner
      - REPORTS OF NAT TURNER'S REBELLION, Niles Weekly Register, August 27, September 3, 1831; Size: Small (Item 873)
      - REPORTS OF OTHER INSURRECTIONS, Niles Weekly Register, September 24, 1831; Size: Small (Item 874)
      - REPORT OF TURNER'S CAPTURE AND HANGING, Niles Weekly Register, November 19, 1831; Size: Small (Item 875)
    - David Walker
      - VERY RARE AND LENGTHY REVIEW OF WALKER'S "APPEAL" IN ONE OF THE EARLIEST ISSUES OF THE LIBERATOR, The Liberator, April 30, 1831 (Item 877)
    - Daniel Webster
      - SPEECH ON MISSOURI COMPROMISE, Lynchburg Virginian, July 29, August 1, 1850 (Item 878)
    - David Wilmot
      - SPEECH ON PROHIBITION OF SLAVERY IN NEW TERRITORIES, National Era, August 17, 1848 (Item 879)
  - Civil War Period
    - Judah P. Benjamin (Secretary of State for the Confederacy)
      - SPEECH ON LAST CALL TO ARMS AND ARMING OF BLACKS BY THE INTELLECTUAL GIANT OF CONFEDERACY, New York Times, February 13, 1865 (Item 747)
    - John Wilkes Booth
      - LETTER EXPLAINING HIS MOTIVES REGARDING LINCOLN WRITTEN IN LATE 1864, New York Herald, April 20, 1865 (Item 1042)
        Recovered from his sister while he was on the run before he was shot.
    - John Brown
      - LETTER ON BATTLE OF OSAWATOMIE, New York Times, October 25, 1859 (Item 748)
      - TRIAL AND SPEECH BEFORE SENTENCING, New York Times, November 3, 1859 (Item 749)
        See: Frederick Douglass 762
      - LETTER TO A QUAKER LADY, New York Times, November 7, 1859 (Item 1035)
        See Frederick Douglass 763
      - LETTER TO MRS. CHILD, New York Times, November 14, 1859 (Item 750)
      - LAST LETTER TO HIS FAMILY, Daily Pioneer and Democrat, December 10, 1859 (Item 751)
      - LETTER TO REV. J. W. MCFARLAND LESS THAN 10 DAYS BEFORE BEING HANGED AND COOK'S (BROWN ASSOCIATE) LAST LETTER TO HIS WIFE AND CHILD, New York Tribune, December 21, 1859 (Item 1045)
        Brown's very heartfelt and spiritual unburdening at the prospect of death.
    - Jefferson Davis
      - PROCLAMATION THREATENING UNION OFFICERS, New York Times, December 28, 1862 (Item 758)
      - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE VINDICATING THE RIGHTEOUSNESS OF THE CONFEDERACY AND THE INSTITUTION OF SLAVERY, AND THE UNNATURALNESS OF THE EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION WHICH WILL LEAD TO THE EXTERMINATION OF THE BLACKS AND THEIR SERVILE INSURRECTION AGAINST THEIR PEACEFUL MASTERS, New York Herald, January 17, 1863 (Item 1070)
      - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE TO CONFEDERATE CONGRESS, New York Tribune, November 11, 1864 (Item 759)
      - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE (SEE LINCOLN PROCLAMATION ON THANKSGIVING), The Crisis, November 23, 1864 (Item 1071)
    - Frederick Douglass
      - LETTER DISAVOWING CONNECTION TO BROWN'S RAID, New York Times, November 3, 1859 (Item 762)
        Includes John Brown 749
      - LETTER ON JOHN BROWN AND SLAVERY, New York Times, November 7, 1859 (Item 763)
      - EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION AND NEGRO SOLDIERS SPEECH, New York Daily Tribune, February 7, 1863 (Item 764)
      - MEN OF COLOR CALL TO ARMS SPEECH, New York Daily Tribune, March 5, 1863 (Item 765)
      - EMANCIPATION IN MARYLAND SPEECH, Commonwealth, November 26, 1864 (Item 766)
      - WHAT THE BLACK MAN WANTS SPEECH, Commonwealth, February 25, 1865 (Item 767)
      - AMERICAN ANTI-SLAVERY SOCIETY SPEECH, New York Times, May 11, 1865 (Item 768)
      - LETTER TO PRESIDENT JOHNSON ON BLACKS VERUS WHITES, New York Times, February 9, 1866 (Item 769)
      - THOUGHTS ON SAN DOMINGO AFTER A VISIT, Daily State Journal, May 4, 1871 (Item 770)
      - RESOLUTIONS ON BLACK TREATMENT IN SOUTH, New York Tribune, February 2, 1875 (Item 771)
      - EXTRACT OF A LETTER ON THE FATE OF THE SOUTH AND THE VINDICATION OF HIS OWN EFFORTS ON BEHALF OF THE NEGRO, New York Times, January 19, 1879 (Item 1032)
      - LETTER ON GREATNESS OF JOHN BROWN, New York Times, April 30, 1881 (Item 772)
      - ARTICLE ON THE CONDITION OF THE FREEDMEN, Harper's Weekly, December 8, 1883; Size: Small (Item 1009)
    - John Fremont
      - GENERAL FREMONT'S EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION, New York Tribune, September 2, 1861 (Item 773)
        Anticipating Lincoln and rescinded by Lincoln.
    - William Lloyd Garrison
      - ANTI-SLAVERY SPEECH, The Liberator, July 12, 1861 (Item 774)
        See: Wendell Phillips 846
    - Ulysses S. Grant
      - LETTER TO CONGRESSMAN MORRIS REGARDING THE INFAMOUS GENERAL ORDER NO. 11 WHICH LINCOLN RESCINDED, AND LETTER OF ADOLPH MOSES, New York Times, November 30, 1868 (Item 776)
        Order No. 11, issued by Grant in December 1862, ordered the expulsion of Jews from the Department of the Tennessee due to suspicion of illegal trade. This letter is the only public explanation Grant ever offered on the subject as it was broached during the 1868 presidential campaign.
        See Reconstruction 776
      - PROCLAMATION SUSPENDING HABEAS CORPUS AND SOUTH CAROLINA KU KLUX KLAN, New York Times, October 18, 1871 (Item 1055)
        The Enforcement Acts, three bills passed in 1870-71, were criminal codes that supposedly protected African-Americans' rights to vote, hold office, and to serve on juries and receive equal protection under the law. Grant, who was tired of the violent tactics of the Ku Klux Klan, ordered them to disperse from South Carolina and lay down their arms under the authority of the Enforcement Acts. There was no response, so Grant issued a suspension of habeas corpus in nine counties of South Carolina, ordering troops in the state to round up and disarm the Klan.
        See Reconstruction 1055
    - David Hunter
      - GENERAL HUNTER'S EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION, New York Tribune, May 20, 1862 (Item 777)
      - LETTER VINDICATING USE OF BLACK TROOPS, The Liberator, July 11, 1862 (Item 778)
        See: Wendell Phillips 850
      - LETTER AGAINST SLAVERY AND THE NEED TO USE BLACK TROOPS, The New York Times, August 6, 1862 (Item 1072)
        One of the most liberal generals in the US Army, Hunter freed the blacks on his own in 1862 in the vast territory that he controlled, only to have Lincoln rescind his order to placate the border states (See item 777).
        Also contains PARAPHRASE OF A SPEECH BY WENDELL PHILLIPS ON THE WAR
    - Andrew Johnson
      - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, The World, December 3, 1867 (Item 791)
        The most racist speech by an American president.
        See Reconstruction 791
      - RACIST VETO OF FREEDMEN'S BILL AND RANTING AND PARANOID SPEECH TALKING OF PRO-BLACK RADICAL REPUBLICANS AS TRAITORS AND ASSASSINS AND COMPARING HIMSELF TO CHRIST AND WILLING TO UNDERGO MARTYRDOM, New York Times, February 23, 1866 (Item 786)
        See Reconstruction 786
      - RACIST VETO OF CIVIL RIGHTS BILL, New York Times, March 28, 1866 (Item 787)
        See Reconstruction 787
      - PROCLAMATION ON THE END OF THE CONFEDERATE INSURRECTION (CIVIL WAR), The World (New York), April 3, 1866 (Item 1052)
        War was not waged for the purpose of conquest or subjugation, nor for overthrowing or interfering with the rights or established institutions of the states, but to defend the Constitution and preserve the Union. War was forced upon the country by disunionists of the South.
      - RACIST AND DEFAMATORY CAMPAIGN SPEECHES, New York Herald, September 10, 1866 (Item 788)
        See Reconstruction 788
      - RACIST AND DEFAMATORY CAMPAIGN SPEECHES, New York Times, September 13, 1866 (Item 789)
        See Reconstruction 789
      - VETO OF THE FIRST RECONSTRUCTION ACT, New York Times, March 4, 1867 (Item 1053)
        Johnson, a sympathizer of the south and a slaveholder, despite being an avowed unionist, wants the military governments in the southern states to lighten the burden of draconian regulations and make the oppressive atmosphere of military rule less prevalent. He seems to have a problem with Negroes being allowed to vote, especially since they haven't asked for that right. He considers the purpose of the bill to change the character and structure of the state governments, and to compel them to accept laws they are unwilling to accept if left to themselves. He, like the South, was never fully contrite or acknowledged the sin of slavery. He considers the powers given to military officers amounts to absolute despotism, and the nine million southerners are bereft of any legal defense, since local control is overridden by the military.
      - RACIST VETO OF SUPPLEMENTARY RECONSTRUCTION BILL, New York Times, March 24, 1867 (Item 790)
        See Reconstruction 790
      - PROCLAMATION RESTORING ALL RIGHTS TO REBELLION PARTICIPANTS, New York Weekly Tribune, September 11, 1867 (Item 1054)
        Restoration of all property except as to slaves and that civil authority might be reestablished as long as its legislation will conform to the condition of affairs growing out of the amendment to the Constitution prohibiting slavery. In many cases the former slaveholders had to take loyalty oaths and deliver them personally to Johnson, who had always hated the genteel landowners, as he came from the lowest and poorest class of whites. This is his revenge. He wanted to avoid in general a retaliatory and vindictive policy with its attendant pains, disqualifications, penalties and disenfranchisements, and have the former southern members of Congress seated and brought back into the government. The Radical Republicans would impeach Johnson for his obstructionist policies during Reconstruction and his leniency to the unrepentant South.
      - JOHNSON'S IMPEACHMENT TRIAL, New York Tribune, May 6, 1868 (Item 792)
    - Robert E. Lee
      - LETTER TO GENERAL ROSECRANS ON RECONSTRUCTION PROSPECTS AND BLACK INFERIORITY AND EXPULSION OF BLACK MEMBERS FROM GEORGIA LEGISLATURE, New York Times, September 5, 1868 (Item 794)
    - Lewis and Clark
      - ABOUT TO LEAVE AND AT LOUISVILLE, The Balance, October 4, December 6, 1803; Size: Small (Item 395)
      - LETTER FROM LEWIS TO JEFFERSON FROM FORT MANDAN, New England Palladium, July 26, 1805 (Item 396)
        The only communication published during the expedition and one of the most historic letters in American history.
      - LETTER FROM LEWIS TO JEFFERSON FROM FORT MANDAN, The Balance, August 13, 1805; Size: Small (Item 397)
      - SPECIMENS FROM THE EXPEDITION, The Balance, September 17, 1805; Size: Small (Item 398)
      - MEN FROM EXPEDTION AND INDIANS AT ST. LOUIS, The Balance, November 5, 1805; Size: Small (Item 399)
      - MESSAGE FROM JEFFERSON TO CONGRESS DESCRIBING MISSION OF LEWIS AND CLARK, United States' Gazette for the Country, February 28, 1806 (Item 400)
      - MESSAGE FROM JEFFERSON TO CONGRESS DESCRIBING MISSION OF LEWIS AND CLARK, Alexandria Daily Advertiser, March 1, 1806 (Item 401)
      - LETTER FROM CLARK TO BROTHER, Aurora, November 3, 1806 (Item 402)
        Very famous letter.
      - CELEBRATORY DINNER GIVEN LEWIS ON HIS RETURN FEATURING THE FIRST APPEARANCE OF THE FAMOUS POEM BY JOEL BARLOW "ON THE DISCOVERIES OF CAPTAIN LEWIS," National Intelligencer, January 16, 1807 (Item 403)
        Suggesting the renaming of the Columbia to Lewis River.
      - LEWIS LETTER ON UNAUTHORIZED BOOKS, National Intelligencer, March 27, 1807 (Item 404)
      - PROSPECTUS FOR PUBLISHING OFFICIAL ACCOUNT OF EXPEDITION AND LEWIS' SIG. AFTER DESCRIBING MAP OF NORTH AMERICA, National Intelligencer, July 31, 1807 (Item 405)
      - LETTER FROM NATHANIEL PRYOR (SERGEANT IN THE LEWIS AND CLARK EXPEDITION) TO GENERAL WILLIAM CLARK (INDIAN AGENT), FRENCH-BRITISH RELATIONS, New York Herald, November 25, 1807 (Item 969)
    - Abraham Lincoln
      - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Boston Evening Transcript, December 4, 1861 (Item 811)
      - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, New York Tribune, December 2, 1862 (Item 823)
      - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, New York Times, December 10, 1863 (Item 834)
        Supplement to the New York Times.
      - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, New York Tribune, December 7, 1864 (Item 837)
      - LINCOLN AND DOUGLAS DEBATE AT FREEPORT, New York Tribune, September 1, 1858 (Item 796)
        Also features letter from Elizabeth Cady Stanton (page 6) declining the invitation to join the "Lady Managers" of the Mount Vernon Association, stating: "Until we give the world freedom, and a new type of womanhood, we have no energies to spend elsewhere."
      - SPEECH AT CINCINNATI ON SLAVERY, National Intelligencer, September 22, 1859 (Item 797)
      - COOPER UNION SPEECH, New York Times, February 28, 1860 (Item 798)
      - LETTER ON RIGHTS OF NATURALIZED CITIZENS, New York Times, May 29, 1860 (Item 799)
      - SENTIMENTS OF THE PRESIDENT ON THE SECESSION QUESTION, New York Herald, November 23, 1860 (Item 800)
      - FAREWELL SPEECH AT SPRINGFIELD AS PRESIDENT ELECT, New York Tribune, February 12, 1861 (Item 801)
      - SPEECHES AT CINCINNATI AND INDIANAPOLIS AS PRESIDENT ELECT, New York Tribune, February 13, 1861 (Item 802)
      - SPEECH AT BUFFALO AS PRESIDENT ELECT, New York Tribune, February 18, 1861 (Item 803)
      - SPEECH AT NEW YORK AS PRESIDENT ELECT, New York Tribune, February 21, 1861 (Item 804)
      - PROCLAMATION DECLARING START OF CIVIL WAR AND FORT SUMTER, New York Daily Tribune, April 15, 1861 (Item 805)
      - MESSAGE TO CONGRESS ON THE CAUSE, PURPOSE, AND CONSTITUTIONALITY OF THE WAR, New York Herald, July 6, 1861 (Item 806)
        One of Lincoln's little known great speeches.
      - PROCLAMATION ON REBEL PROPERTY, New York Herald, August 17, 1861 (Item 807)
      - LETTER TO GOVERNOR OF KENTUCKY ON TROOP REMOVAL, The Crisis, September 12, 1861 (Item 808)
      - LETTER TO GENERAL JOHN FREMONT ON RESCINDING HIS EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION, New York Herald, September 15, 1861 (Item 809)
      - PROCLAMATION ON NATIONAL FAST DAY, Davenport Daily Gazette, September 26, 1861 (Item 810)
      - LETTER REFUSING TO PARDON SLAVE-TRADER CAPTAIN NATHANIEL GORDON BEFORE HE IS TO BE HANGED, New York Herald, February 7, 1862 (Item 1044)
        Lincoln stays the execution for two weeks to allow Gordon to get his affairs in order. Gordon was the first and only slave-trader in the history of the United States to be tried, convicted, and hanged in accordance with the Constitution and federal law. On August 7, 1860 897 slaves were taken on board his ship, Erie, in West Africa, 334 adults and the rest children. It was said he preferred them because they could not rebel against his cruelties. His ship was captured by USS Mohican. Despite Lincoln's well-known compassion and inclination to issue pardons, this he could not abide. The trial judge, Worcester Aegis, said, "Think of the sufferings of the unhappy beings whom you crowded on the Erie; of their helpless agony and terror as you took them from their native land; …Do not flatter yourself that because they belonged to a different race from yourself, your guilt is therefore lessened— rather fear that it is increased. In the just and generous heart, the humble and the weak inspire compassion, and call for pity and forbearance. As you are soon to pass into the presence of that god of the black man as well as the white man, who is no respecter of persons, do not indulge for a moment the thought that he hears with indifference the cry of the humblest of his children. On another related case, perhaps less egregious, Lincoln had said, "I believe I am kindly enough in nature and can be moved to pity and to pardon the perpetrator of almost the worst crime that the mind of man can conceive or the arm of man can execute; but any man, who, for paltry gain and stimulated only by avarice, can rob Africa of her children to sell into interminable bondage, I never will pardon, and he may stay and rot in jail before he will ever get relief from me."
      - MESSAGE TO CONGRESS RECOMMENDING COMPENSATED EMANCIPATION AND MONITOR AND MERRIMACK, Newark Advocate, March 14, 1862 (Item 812)
      - MESSAGE ON EMANCIPATION OF SLAVERY IN DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA, The Crisis, April 23, 1862 (Item 813)
      - PROCLAMATION RESCINDING GENERAL DAVID HUNTER'S EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION, The Liberator, May 23, 1862 (Item 814)
        See: Wendell Phillips 849
      - APPEAL TO BORDER STATES AND ADDRESS OF REPRESENTATIVE MEMBERS OF CONGRESS, New York Tribune, July 19, 1862 (Item 815)
        Going over Lincoln's head to make the case for arming blacks.
      - ENFORCEMENT OF THE CONFISCATION ACT, New York Herald, July 23, 1862 (Item 816)
      - SPEECH ON FIGHT BETWEEN MCCLELLAN AND STANTON, New York Tribune, August 7, 1862 (Item 817)
      - MEETING AT WHITE HOUSE WITH FREE BLACKS, New York Tribune, August 15, 1862 (Item 819)
        Full Title: "The Colonization of People of African Descent. Interview with President Lincoln. Speech of the President. He holds that the White and Black Races Cannot Dwell Together. He urges Colored Men to Exert Themselves for Colonization. He suggests Central America as the Colony."
      - MEETING AT WHITE HOUSE WITH FREE BLACKS, The Liberator, August 22, 1862 (Item 820)
      - PROCLAMATION SUSPENDING WRIT OF HABEAS CORPUS AND REPLY TO SERENADE IN HONOR OF EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION, New York Times, September 25, 1862 (Item 821)
      - LETTER TO HORACE GREELEY, Pittsburgh Post, October 4, 1862 (Item 822)
      - ADDRESS OF THE COLORED PEOPLE OF THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA TO PRESIDENT LINCOLN, New York Herald, November 3, 1862 (Item 1064)